Chapter 57. Of whales in paint, in teeth, in wood, in sheet iron, in stone,
in mountains, in stars.
On Tower Hill, as you go down to the London docks, you may have seen a
crippled beggar, or kedger, as the sailors say, holding a painted board
before him, representing the tragic scene in which he lost his leg. There
are three whales and three boats, and one of the boats, presumed to contain
the missing leg in all its original integrity, is being crunched by the jaws
of the foremost whale. Any time these 10 years, they tell me, has that man held
up that picture, and exhibited that stump to an incredulous world? But the
time of his justification has now come.
His three whales are as good whales as were ever published in whopping at any
rate, and his stump as unquestionable a stump as any you will find in the
western clearings. But though forever mounted on that stump, never a stump
speech does the poor whaleman make, but with downcast eyes stands rofully
contemplating his own amputation.
Throughout the Pacific and also in Nantucket and New Bedford and Sag
Harbor, you will come across lively sketches of whales and whailing scenes
graven by the fishermen themselves on sperm whale teeth or ladies busks rot
out of the right whale bone or other like scrimshander articles as the
whalemen call the numerous little ingenious contrivances they elaborately
carve out of the rough material in their hours of ocean leisure.
Some of them have little boxes of dentisticl looking implements specially
intended for the scrimshandering business, but in general they toil with
their jack knives alone, and with that almost omnipotent tool of the sailor,
they will turn you out anything you please in the way of a mariner's fancy.
Long exile from Christrysendom and civilization inevitably restores a man
to that condition in which God placed him, i.e. e what is called savagery.
Your true whale hunter is as much a savage as an irakqua. I myself am a
savage, owing no allegiance but to the king of the cannibals, and ready at any
moment to rebel against him. Now, one of the peculiar characteristics of the
savage in his domestic hours is his wonderful patience of industry. An
ancient Hawaiian war club or spear paddle in its full multiplicity and
elaboration of carving is as great a trophy of human perseverance as a Latin
lexicon. For with but a bit of broken sea shell or a shark's tooth, that
miraculous intricacy of wooden network has been achieved, and it has cost
steady years of steady application.
As with the Hawaiian savage, so with the whale sailor savage, with the same
marvelous patience, and with the same single sharks tooth of his one poor jack
knife, he will carve you a bit of bone sculpture, not quite as workmanlike, but
as close packed in its maziness of design as the Greek savage Achilles
shield, and full of barbaric spirit and suggestiveness as the prince of that
fine old Dutch Savage Albertch Durer.
Wooden whales or whales cut in profile out of the small dark slabs of the noble
South Sea warwood are frequently met with in the folks of American whalers.
Some of them are done with much accuracy.
At some old gable roofed country houses you will see brass whales hung by the
tail for knockers to the roadside door.
When the porter is sleepy, the anvil-headed whale would be best. But
these knocking whales are seldom remarkable as faithful essays. On the
spires of some old-fashioned churches, you will see sheet iron whales placed
there for weathercocks, but they are so elevated, and besides that are to all
intents and purposes so labeled with hands off, you cannot examine them
closely enough to decide upon their merit.
in bony riby regions of the earth where at the base of high broken cliffs masses
of rock lie strewn in fantastic groupings upon the plane. You will often
discover images as of the petrified forms of the Leviathan partly merged in
grass which of a windy day breaks against them in a surf of green surges.
Then again in mountainous countries where the traveler is continually
girdled by amphitheatrical heights here and there from some lucky point of view
you will catch passing glimpses of the profiles of whales defined along the
undulating ridges. But you must be a thorough whaleman to see these sites.
And not only that, but if you wish to return to such a site again, you must be
sure and take the exact intersecting latitude and longitude of your first
standpoint, else so chance-like are such observations of the hills, that your
precise previous standpoint would require a laborious rediscovery, like
the Salom Islands, which still remain incognito, though once high rough Madana
trod them, and old Figua chronicled Nor when expandingly lifted by your
subject can you fail to trace out great whales in the starry heavens and boats
in pursuit of them. As when long filled with thoughts of war the eastern nations
saw armies locked in battle among the clouds. Thus at the north have I chased
Leviathan round and round the pole with the revolutions of the bright points
that first defined him to me. And beneath the eulgent Antarctic skies, I
have boarded the Argo Navvice and joined the chase against the starry Satus far
beyond the utmost stretch of Hydrris and the flying fish.
With a frigot's anchors for my bridal bits and fies of harpoons for spurs,
would I could mount that whale and leap the topmost skies to see whether the
fabled heavens, with all their countless tents, really lie encamped beyond my mortal sight.